Eastman mss. II, 1869-1981 LMC 2427
Lilly Library
Eastman mss. II
1869-1981
2001
Lilly Library
Eastman, Max, 1883-1969
LMC 2427
44 Boxes
The Eastman mss. II, 1869-1981, consist of the correspondence, writings, personal papers, and photographs of Max Eastman, 1883-1969.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Completing his work for a Ph.D. degree at Columbia and encouraged by John Dewey, Max Eastman taught logic for three years at the University. In 1909 Eastman organized the Men's League for Woman's Suffrage. His marriage to Ida Rauh, actress and poet, occurred in 1911 and produced comment when it was learned Miss Rauh would retain her maiden name. Their son Daniel was born in 1912. A year later Eastman's first books, Enjoyment of Poetry and Child of the Amazons, were published. During this time he became editor of The Masses with its new idea in format and inclination toward then-radical causes and worked with it until its close in October, 1917. The next year with his sister Crystal Eastman as co-owner he started a new periodical with similar interests called The Liberator.
Leaving The Liberator in the hands of others in 1922 Eastman attended the International Conference at Genoa, Italy, where he met the secretary to Maxim Litvinoff, Eliena Krylenko, 1895-1956, artist and dancer. Continuing on to Russia the two met again and were married in 1924. Their correspondence may be found in the Eastman, E., mss. (The divorce from Miss Rauh had been effected in 1922). During a sojourn of five years in Europe Eastman became acquainted with Leon Trotsky, served as his literary agent in the United States, and translated some of his works. The correspondence for this relationship may be found in the Trotskii mss. Pursuing his interests in writing and lecturing on Russia, socialism, literature, humor, and poetry, Eastman became engaged as a roving editor for The Reader's Digest Association for a number of years.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into eight series: Correspondence, Personal, Translations, Writings and Works, Speeches and Lectures, Photographs, Miscellaneous, and Audio-Visual. Materials within Writings and Works are arranged when possible according to their corresponding publication or work; these subseries are then arranged chronologically in order of publication or appearance. All folders are arranged alphabetically when possible and retain Max Eastman's original folder titles and groupings when possible.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the collection consists of Eastman's notes, research, drafts, and subject files related to his prolific body of writings, sorted into their corresponding publication subseries when possible. Though the Personal series contains the bulk of material relating to Max's personal life, there are several folders within the Love and Revolution and Enjoyment of Living subseries of Writings and Works that pertain to his life history and the lives of his family members; because these folders served as research/subject files for Eastman's memoirs, they reside with the other corresponding materials for those publications. A substantial collection of Eastman's notes and drafts for speeches and lectures on a number of subjects, as well as a small collection of photographs, complete the collection.
Related Material
See Eastman mss., Eastman mss. III, Eastman mss. IV, and Eastman mss. V, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2001
Labor unions and socialism; Slavs; Russia; Eastman, Max, 1883-1969
- I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1896 (Box 1)
  - 1910-1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920-1929 (Box 1)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - 1950-1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - Benson, Geo. C. S., 1953-1958 (Box 1)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1954-1957 (Box 1)
  - Calverton, V. F. ("George"), 1935-1962 (Box 1)
  - Debs, E. V., 1918 (Box 1)
  - Deshon, Florence, 1917-1921; (2 folders) (Box 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes photo
  - Dewey, John, 1933 (Box 1)
  - Dreiser, Theodore, 1929-1934 (Box 1)
  - Einstein, Albert, 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - Farrar, Straus, and Cudahy, Inc., 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Filer, Tom, 1956-1965 (Box 1)
  - Freud, Sigmund, 1926-1936 (Box 1)
  - Goddard, Paulette, undated (Box 1)
  - "Helping The New Leader, 1945-1946 (Box 1)
  - Horizon Press, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Keller, Helen (via Marguerite Levine), 1917? (Box 1)
  - "Letters drafted for Reader's Digest undated (Box 1)
  - "Letters re: 'We Must Face the Facts' - Against", 1943 (Box 1)
  - "Letters re: 'We Must Face the Facts' - For", 1943; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Lindsay, Vachel, 1918 (Box 1)
  - "Max's Fan Letters", 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous transcribed letters, undated (Box 1)
  - Mulholland, Inez, 1909-1916? (Box 1)
  - "My objections to the presentation of [Tsar to Lenin],", 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Nancy", 1920 (Box 1)
  - Pavlov, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Random House, 1962-1965 (Box 2)
  - Rauh, Ida, 1913-1918 (Box 2)
  - Rauh, Ida - "Europe", 1911 (Box 2)
  - Rauh, Ida - "Final letters", 1918? (Box 2)
  - "Re: [John] Dewey", 1941 (Box 2)
  - Re: Max's death, 1969; (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Re: Mercersburg, 1958 (Box 2)
  - "Re: refugees", 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Santayana, 1935-1951 (Box 2)
  - Shaw, George Bernard, 1917-1927 (Box 2)
  - Sloan, John, 1913-1948 (Box 2)
  - Souvarine, Boris (via Ginette Merrill), 1937-1967; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - "To Grandfather", 1895 (Box 2)
  - Walling, English, undated (Box 2)
  - Webster, Annie M., 1938? (Box 2)
- II. PERSONAL
  - "Auto-analysis", 1930 (Box 2)
  - "Biographical outlines", 1961-1969? (Box 2)
  - "Books to buy," undated (Box 2)
  - "Books to read", 1957? (Box 2)
  - Clippings about Max, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Contents of Max's "black alligator wallet," undated (Box 2)
    RESTRICTED
  - Diaries, 1932/1952; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Eliena Krylenko materials, 1922-1924? (Box 2)
  - "Europe 1955", 1951-1955 (Box 2)
  - Florence Deshon materials, 1917-1920? (Box 2)
  - Florence Norton materials, 1948-1958 (Box 2)
  - "From Lyricism to Anti-Stalinism: the Disillusionment of Max Eastman" by Lee Lowenfish, 1968 (Box 2)
  - "From Max's desk," undated (Box 2)
  - "Japan - expenses and receipts", 1965 (Box 3)
  - Ireland travel ephemera, 1951-1956; (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - "List of books with letters in them", 1939-1957 (Box 3)
  - "Love and Marriage" clippings, 1912? (Box 3)
  - Max's obituaries, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Medical notes and documents, undated (Box 3)
  - "My character", 1930-1938 (Box 3)
  - Passport and travel documents, 1965? (Box 3)
  - "Poems and their answers," undated (Box 3)
  - Unidentified cat hairs (and one whisker), undated (Box 44)
- III. TRANSLATIONS
  - Pushkin, Alexander
    - Gabriel photocopy, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Young Lenin
    - Ch. 3-12, xerox of annotated typescript, undated (Box 3)
    - Russian text and translation, undated (Box 3)
- IV. WRITINGS AND WORKS
  - Enjoyment of Poetry
    - "Poetry as nature (early essays)", 1903-1908 (Box 3)
  - Child of the Amazons
    - Annotated typescript draft, undated (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1913 (Box 3)
  - Journalism versus Art
    - "Why English does not simplify her spelling", 1909 (Box 3)
  - The Masses
    - Ad re: John Barber's work, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Echoes of Revolt reviews, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
    - Editorials and articles, 1916-1917 (Box 3)
    - "The Masses versus The New Masses,", 1916-1949 (Box 3)
    - "Re: Masses anthology,", 1966 (Box 3)
  - Sense of Humor
    - "Good and bad jokes (to diagram a joke), undated (Box 3)
    - Manuscript notes, undated (Box 3)
    - "Notes and references," undated (Box 3)
    - "Varieties," undated (Box 3)
  - Since Lenin Died
    - "Notes on Steffens and McKay," undated (Box 3)
  - Marx and Lenin
    - Ch. 1, IX-X page proofs, undated (Box 3)
    - Notebooks, 1924? (Box 3)
    - Notes, revisions and remarks, 1927-1937 (Box 3)
    - Preface to second edition, 1935? (Box 3)
    - "Replies to critics", 1927-1928 (Box 3)
    - "Translations for Marx and Lenin," undated (Box 3)
  - The Literary Mind
    - Drafts, undated (Box 3)
    - "The future of literature", 1931 (Box 4)
    - "Literature on the defensive", 1930 (Box 4)
    - "Modernism", 1930 (Box 4)
    - "Psychology of poetry", 1931 (Box 4)
    - Reviews, 1932 (Box 4)
  - Artists in Uniform
    - "I. International Union of Revolutionary Writers", 1931 (Box 4)
    - "II. The Experience of the Soviet Union", 1930-1933 (Box 4)
    - "III. Dialectic Method in Art," undated (Box 4)
    - "IV. Art and Practical Life", 1929-1932 (Box 4)
    - "Not important [research material]", 1938-1955 (Box 4)
    - Notes and inserts, 1933-1934 (Box 4)
    - "Reply to Freeman", 1933 (Box 4)
    - "The word dialectic", 1966? (Box 4)
  - Art and the Life of Action
    - Page proofs, undated (Box 4)
    - Reviews, 1935 (Box 4)
  - The Last Stand of Dialectic Materialism
    - Research and notes, 1928-1933 (Box 4)
  - Enjoyment of Laughter
    - "American and English humor", 1936 (Box 4)
    - "Books on humor", 1934-1935 (Box 4)
    - "Clippings", 1931-1934 (Box 4)
    - "Exaggeration," undated (Box 4)
    - "Humorists on humor", 1934-1936 (Box 4)
    - "Humorous truth", 1929? (Box 4)
    - "Illustrations", 1929 (Box 4)
    - "Irony and exaggeration," undated (Box 4)
    - "Mark Twain", 1935 (Box 4)
    - Notebooks, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - "Parts I & II," undated (Box 4)
    - "Part next-to-last: American humorists", 1931-1936 (Box 4)
    - "Part last: theory," undated (Box 4)
    - "Play-things," undated (Box 4)
    - "Poetic jokes," undated (Box 4)
    - "Poetic with a point," undated (Box 4)
    - "Practical jokes," undated (Box 4)
    - "Royal Jokes," undated (Box 5)
    - "Sarcasm," undated (Box 5)
    - "Satire and sympathetic humor", 1934 (Box 5)
    - "Sex jokes and slapstick," undated (Box 5)
    - "Small punishments", 1934 (Box 5)
    - "Sourpuss laughter", 1948-1954 (Box 5)
    - "Ten commandments," undated (Box 5)
    - "To go in," undated (Box 5)
    - "Understatement and irony," undated (Box 5)
    - "Wit, puns and wise-cracks", 1935 (Box 5)
  - Tsar to Lenin
    - Legal, 1930 (Box 5)
    - Correspondence and publicity, 1937-1957 (Box 5)
  - Stalin's Russia and the Crisis in Socialism
    - "End of socialism in Russia", 1934-1936; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - "For insertion and proof correction", 1939 (Box 5)
    - "Introduction to Spanish edition," undated (Box 5)
    - Reviews, undated (Box 5)
    - "What to do", 1935-1937; (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Marxism: is it a Science?
    - "Marxism vs. science", 1936-1939 (Box 5)
    - Reviews, 1940 (Box 5)
    - "Seed of the Marxian philosophy," undated (Box 5)
    - "Trotsky defends the faith", 1939? (Box 5)
    - "What science is", 1930-1935 (Box 5)
  - Reader's Digest
    - "All my articles for R.D.", 1932-1963; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - "America's philosopher [John Dewey]", 1952; (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - "Barbados", 1966-1967 (Box 5)
    - "Berenson," undated (Box 5)
    - "Bird navigation", 1957? (Box 5)
    - "Bring 'em up alive", 1944 (Box 5)
    - "Buber-Faust", 1951 (Box 5)
    - Contracts and correspondence, 1959-1963 (Box 6)
    - "Conversation in the zoo", 1950 (Box 6)
    - "Conversation with a dentist", 1950 (Box 6)
    - "Culbertson," undated (Box 6)
    - "Don't be bufalloed by unintelligible art", 1950-1954 (Box 6)
    - "The earthly paradise", 1960 (Box 6)
    - "El presidente", 1940-1960; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - "Enjoyment of thinking", 1948-1957 (Box 6)
    - "A footnote to Churchill", 1950? (Box 6)
    - "For animal sociology articles", 1958 (Box 6)
    - "For R. D.", 1961-1963 (Box 6)
    - "The golden age of Pericles," undated (Box 6)
    - "'The Greeks are still Greek' and other writings on Greece", 1947-1949; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - "Hawaii," undated (Box 6)
    - "Ideas for R. D.", 1941-1963 (Box 6)
    - "In praise of Norway", 1955 (Box 6)
    - "Ivan Mestrovic", 1933-1947 (Box 6)
    - "Key concepts in Western civilization", 1953 (Box 6)
    - "Last words", 1942? (Box 6)
    - "Let's close the muscle gap", 1959-1961; (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - "Life in the Soviet Union (and humor)", 1945 (Box 6)
    - "The lost art of oratory", 1954 (Box 6)
    - "Love among the insects", 1959 (Box 6)
    - "Makronissos - isle of enlightenment", 1949-1950 (Box 6)
    - "Mark Twain's experience", 1956 (Box 6)
    - "Mark Twain", 1963 (Box 7)
    - "The miracle of German recovery", 1951; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Moby Dick story", 1957-1961; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Morse Plan", 1949 (Box 7)
    - "Mrs. Ottesen-Jensen and Sweden's sex education", 1949-1957; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "My relation with Reader's Digest,", 1948-1952 (Box 7)
    - "New life for Zeiss", 1951 (Box 7)
    - "Notes for article on Firenze [Florence]", 1954-1960; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Notes for article on 'strange animals,'" undated (Box 7)
    - "One world for children", 1949-1952; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Outlaw the Communist Party", 1948-1950; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "The plight of socialism", 1934-1960 (Box 7)
    - "Proposed articles," undated (Box 7)
    - "Protracted conflict", 1961; (2 folders) (Box 7)
    - "Reports etc.", 1944-1945 (Box 7)
    - "Ropke [Wilhelm]", 1950-1951; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Should we pity the animals in the zoo?", 1950 (Box 8)
    - "Slave labor in Russia", 1943?; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "The soil and the microbe", 1949-1950 (Box 8)
    - "Suggestions from Wallace", 1933-1954 (Box 8)
    - "Switzerland: the oasis of Europe", 1951; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "Understanding wild animals", 1957 (Box 8)
    - "What is funny?", 1962 (Box 8)
    - "Where none o' God's children have shoes," undated (Box 8)
  - Heroes I Have Known
    - Back cover (photocopy), undated (Box 8)
    - Charlie Chaplin, 1935-1936? (Box 8)
    - Isadora Duncan, undated (Box 8)
    - John Dewey, 1938-1941; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - "John Reed and the Russian Revolution", 1924-1936 (Box 8)
    - Mark Twain, undated (Box 8)
  - Enjoyment of Living
    - "A new thought sanitarium", 1906-1939; (3 folders) (Box 8)
    - "A search for my wish," undated (Box 8)
    - Annis Eastman correspondence, 1896-1910; (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Annis Eastman materials, 1910-1956?; (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - Annis Eastman sermons and writings, 1907-1910? (Box 9)
    - Anstice "Peter" Eastman materials, 1892-1913 (Box 9)
    - Anstice "Peter" Eastman's writings, undated (Box 9)
    - "At home", 1902-1904 (Box 9)
    - Author's alterations, 1948 (Box 9)
    - Bethel, Maine, 1905-1945 (Box 9)
    - Canadaigua, 1905-1937 (Box 9)
    - "Conquering New York", 1907 (Box 9)
    - "Dad and Mother (after marriage)," correspondence, 1884-1894 (Box 9)
    - "Dad and Mother's essays in school", 1869?; (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - Dr. Jelliffe, 1916? (Box 9)
    - Eastman family genealogical materials, 1930-1949? (Box 9)
      Includes photos
    - Editorial policy, 1912? (Box 9)
    - "Educating the A.P.", 1913-1940 (Box 9)
    - Elmira, 1938 (Box 9)
    - Europe, 1911 (Box 9)
    - "First uncut and unrevised copy", 1939?; (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - "Freshman year", 1900-1901 (Box 10)
    - Glenora, 1903-1950 (Box 10)
    - "Half-given love," undated (Box 10)
    - "How I went to war," undated (Box 10)
    - "I choose revolution", 1912? (Box 10)
    - "Junior year", 1902-1953 (Box 10)
    - "Kicked out of various places", 1916 (Box 10)
    - "Last chapter", 1917? (Box 10)
    - "Like a big river", 1909-1910 (Box 10)
    - "Marxism and marriage", 1911 (Box 10)
    - Mercersburg, 1898-1900 (Box 10)
    - Morgan Eastman correspondence, 1867-1891 (Box 10)
    - Morgan Eastman materials, 1900-1937 (Box 10)
    - "Mother and Father's love letters", 1873-1875 (Box 10)
    - "Mother's death (and her sickness)", 1904-1910 (Box 10)
    - "My Amazon comes true", 1909-1910 (Box 10)
    - "My gravitation loses its earth", 1901-1911 (Box 10)
    - "My soul and the proletariat", 1912-1913 (Box 10)
    - Pages cut from "Self-Analysis," undated (Box 10)
    - Park Church, 1899-1949 (Box 10)
    - "Philosophy in passing", 1907-1956 (Box 10)
    - Provincetown, 1916 (Box 10)
    - Reviews, 1948 (Box 10)
    - "Ruth", 1909-1957 (Box 10)
    - Samuel Eastman correspondence, 1873-1913 (Box 10)
    - Samuel Eastman materials, 1898-1915?; (3 folders) (Box 10)
    - "Senior year", 1904-1905 (Box 10)
    - Separation from Ida, undated (Box 10)
    - Sophomore year, 1901-1902 (Box 10)
    - "Starting The Masses,", 1912-1913 (Box 10)
    - "Towards a new harmony", 1914? (Box 11)
    - "Towards Liberty gets lost,", 1911-1917 (Box 11)
    - "Truth sinks wanly down...", 1911-1912 (Box 11)
    - Vol. I, white carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. I, yellow carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. II, white carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. II-III, yellow carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. III, white carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. IV, white carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. IV, yellow carbon copy, undated, (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Vol. IV, second copy, undated (Box 11)
    - "Wander-months", 1902 (Box 11)
    - West Bloomfield, 1892-1937 (Box 11)
    - "Western trip", 1902 (Box 11)
    - Williamstown, 1905-1906 (Box 11)
  - Poems of Five Decades
    - "Poems left out," undated (Box 12)
    - Reviews, undated (Box 12)
  - Reflections on the Failure of Socialism
    - "Additional reflections", 1955 (Box 12)
    - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Communist immoralism", 1949 (Box 12)
    - "The delinquent liberals", 1946-1953 (Box 12)
    - "Freedom and planned economy", 1950-1952? (Box 12)
    - Introduction to new edition, 1963 (Box 12)
    - "Replacement for the dream we lost", 1948-1952 (Box 12)
    - Reviews, 1955 (Box 12)
    - "Socialism and human nature," undated (Box 12)
    - "Soft-headed liberals", 1940-1952; (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - "To be used in Reflections,", 1948-1952 (Box 12)
    - "What to call yourself", 1947-1953 (Box 12)
    - You Have to Choose introduction, undated (Box 12)
  - Great Companions
    - Annotated typescript, undated (Box 12)
    - "Charlie Chaplin: memories and reflections", 1957? (Box 12)
    - Edna Millay, undated (Box 12)
    - Ernest Hemingway, 1946-1962; (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - E. W. Scripps, 1951 (Box 12)
    - John Dewey, 1955-1959; (2 folders) (Box 12)
    - Pablo Casals, 1952 (Box 12)
    - Reviews, 1959; (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Santayana, 1932-1955 (Box 13)
    - Sigmund Freud, 1949? (Box 13)
    - "Three visits with Einstein," undated (Box 13)
  - Love and Revolution
    - 1917 (Box 13)
    - "1943," research and notes (Box 13)
    - "Anna Louise Strong, Mother Bloor, Dorothy Day", 1936-1949 (Box 13)
    - Annotated typescript, 1961-1963; (11 folders) (Box 13)
    - "At Genoa (and Paris)", 1922 (Box 14)
    - "Austrian interlude (Jotte, Freud)", 1927 (Box 14)
    - Binder (Empty), undated (Box 32 (Oversize))
    - "Bouquets", 1916-1944 (Box 14)
    - "Brickbats", 1941-1944 (Box 14)
    - Ch. I-XIX, final copy, 1961 (Box 14)
    - "Chronologies", 1814-1951 (Box 14)
    - "Chronology to 1930 and 1931", 1927-1930 (Box 14)
    - "Contents of Liberator,", 1918-1922 (Box 14)
    - "Defending an error", 1919-1920 (Box 14)
    - Early annotated typescript, undated, (4 folders) (Box 14)
    - "Escape from socialism", 1953-1956; (3 folders) (Box 14)
    - "Escape from socialism," annotated typescript, undated, (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - "Escape from socialism," yellow copies, undated (Box 14)
    - "Final chapter", 1942-1954 (Box 14)
    - "First Masses trial," undated (Box 14)
    - "Found in bottom drawer," typescript, 1963; (Folders 1-2) (Box 14)
    - "Found in bottom drawer," typescript, 1963; (Folders 3-4) (Box 15)
    - "Friends in the Midi", 1924-1961 (Box 15)
    - Galley proofs, undated (Box 33-34 (Oversize))
    - "Homesick at home", 1928-1961 (Box 15)
    - "The Impact of Lenin", 1918-1919 (Box 15)
    - "In Russia", 1919-1924; (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - Incomplete annotated typescript, 1961; (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - Incomplete carbons, undated, (4 folders) (Box 15)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," annotated typescript, 1962 (Box 15)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," annotated typescript, 1959; (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," appendix, undated (Box 15)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," early typescript, undated, (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," early annotated typescript, 1959; (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," manuscript of revisions, 1959; (4 folders) (Box 16)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," Vol. II, first carbons, 1962 (Box 16)
    - "Journey through an Epoch," yellow carbon, 1959; (3 folders) (Box 16)
    - "Liberator founded,", 1918-1953 (Box 16)
    - "Mike Gold", 1932-1941 (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts used, undated, (2 folders) (Box 16)
    - "My Three Horse Chariot," revised typescript, 1956-1959 (Box 16)
    - "My Three Horse Chariot," Vol. I, undated (Box 16)
    - "My Three Horse Chariot," Vol. II, undated (Box 16)
    - "My Three Horse Chariot," Vol. III, undated (Box 16)
    - "My Three Horse Chariot," Vol. IV, undated (Box 16)
    - Notes and research, 1917-1952; (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Notes on Claude McKay, undated (Box 17)
    - "Pages rejected (or already used)," undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
    - "Pages retyped and inserts typed", 1962; (2 folders) (Box 17)
    - Part I, final carbon, undated, (3 folders) (Box 17)
    - Part II and III, final carbon, undated, (4 folders) (Box 17)
    - "Personae", 1930-1965 (Box 17)
    - "Pilgrimage to Moscow", 1929-1957 (Box 17)
    - Publicity questionnaire, undated (Box 17)
    - "Renouncing the hypothesis", 1914-1953 (Box 18)
    - "Research notes (by year)", 1930-1941; (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - Reviews, 1965; (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - "Russian controversy", 1925-1928 (Box 18)
    - Revised and retyped pages and inserts, 1962; (3 folders) (Box 18)
    - "Second Masses trial,", 1918 (Box 18)
    - Setting copy, undated, (Folders 1-6) (Box 18)
    - Setting copy, undated, (Folder 7) (Box 19)
    - "Socialism as science (or my kind of socialism)", 1952? (Box 19)
    - "Suggestions etc: Floyd Dell", 1950-1962 (Box 19)
    - "Suggestions from Daniel Aron", 1922-1934 (Box 19)
    - "Stopping a world war", 1917-1957 (Box 19)
    - "Trotsky disavows me", 1925-1928; (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - Vol. I-III, annotated typescript, undated, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - "Wilson's was and Russia's revolution", 1938-1956 (Box 19)
    - "Winter in Moscow", 1947? (Box 19)
    - Xeroxed pages, undated (Box 19)
    - "The years of belief", 1949? (Box 19)
    - Yellow carbon copy, 1961; (6 folders) (Box 19)
  - Seven Kinds of Goodness
    - Annotated manuscript, 1952? (Box 19)
    - "Buddha", 1955-1962 (Box 19)
    - "The cardinal virtues," undated (Box 19)
    - "Confucius", 1966 (Box 19)
    - "The duty to grow", 1944-1947 (Box 19)
    - "Jesus as a human teacher", 1961-1965 (Box 19)
    - "Mohammed", 1955-1965 (Box 20)
    - "Moses", 1962-1966 (Box 20)
    - "On coming to Jesus", 1965? (Box 20)
    - "Plato", 1961? (Box 20)
    - Reviews and publicity, 1967 (Box 20)
    - Revised typescript, undated (Box 20)
    - "Socrates", 1954-1966 (Box 20)
    - "Zoroaster," undated (Box 20)
  - The Word Game
    - "Ad libbing", 1938 (Box 20)
    - "Fan mail", 1938 (Box 20)
    - "Ideas (from correspondents)", 1938; (2 folders) (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous, 1938 (Box 20)
    - Scripts, April 1938 (Box 20)
    - Scripts, May 1938 (Box 20)
    - Scripts, June 1938 (Box 20)
    - Scripts, July 1938 (Box 20)